[
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 1,
        "year": 1993,
        "question": "Copper metal will react with concentrated trioxonitrate (V) acid to give?",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 3,
        "options": [
            "Cu(NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub>+ NO + N<sub>2</sub>O<sub>4</sub>+ H<sub>2</sub>O",
            "Cu(NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>+ NO + H<sub>2</sub>O",
            "CuO + NO<sub>2</sub>+ H<sub>2</sub>O",
            "Cu(NO<sub>2</sub>)<sub>3</sub>+ NO<sub>2</sub>+ H<sub>2</sub>O"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 2,
        "year": 1993,
        "question": "Which of the following separation is routinely applied in the petroleum industry",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 4,
        "options": [
            "Filtration",
            "Chromatography",
            "Evaporation",
            "Fractional crystallization",
            "Fractional distillation"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 3,
        "year": 1993,
        "question": "Starch undergoes complete hydrolysis to produce",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 3,
        "options": [
            "maltose",
            "lactose",
            "fructose",
            "glucose",
            "sucrose"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 4,
        "year": 1993,
        "question": "Which of the following solids has a network structure?",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 0,
        "options": [
            "Diamond",
            "lodine",
            "Sulphur",
            "Graphite",
            "lron"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 5,
        "year": 1993,
        "question": "Trioxosulphate (lV) acid is not stored for a long period because it",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 2,
        "options": [
            "is a weak dibasic acid",
            "has bleaching properties",
            "is unstable and eaily decomposed",
            "smells strongly of sulphur (lV) oxide",
            "can act as a germicide"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 6,
        "year": 1993,
        "question": "Alkanes are used mainly",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 1,
        "options": [
            "in the production of plastics",
            "as domestic and industrial fuels",
            "in the textile industry",
            "in the hydrogenation of oils",
            "as fine chemicals"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 7,
        "year": 1993,
        "question": "Which of the following pairs illustrates isotopy?",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 3,
        "options": [
            "But-l-ene and but -2-ene",
            "Ortho-hydrogen and parahydrogen",
            "Oxygen and ozone",
            "Hydrogen and deuterium",
            "Alpha-particle and beta-particle"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 8,
        "year": 1993,
        "question": "Carbon is often deposited in the exhaust-pipe of cars because of the",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 3,
        "options": [
            "presence of carbon in petrol",
            "dehydrogenation of petrol",
            "incomplete combustion of petrol",
            "presence of additives in petrol",
            "contamination of petrol with diesel"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 9,
        "year": 1993,
        "question": "What does X atand for in the following expression? X = Log<sub>(10)</sub>(H<sup>+</sup>)",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 3,
        "options": [
            "Enthalpy change (∆H)",
            "Equilibrium constant (K)",
            "Solubility product",
            "Degree of acidity (pH)",
            "lonic product of water"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 10,
        "year": 1993,
        "question": "Sulphur burns in air to form",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 0,
        "options": [
            "an acidic oxide",
            "a basic oxide",
            "an amphoteric oxide",
            "a neutra oxide",
            "a mixed oxide"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 11,
        "year": 1993,
        "question": "In which of the following changes is ∆S negative ?",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 0,
        "options": [
            "H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>(l)</sub>→ H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>(s)</sub>",
            "C<sub>(s)</sub>+ 1/2O<sub>2,/sub&gt;<sub>(g)</sub> → CO<sub>(g)</sub>\n</sub>",
            "PCI<sub>5</sub><sub>(g)</sub>→ PCl<sub>3</sub><sub>(g)</sub>+ Cl<sub>2</sub><sub>(g)</sub>",
            "NaCl<sub>(s)</sub>+ aq →Na<sub>+</sub><sub>(aq)</sub>+ Cl<sub>-</sub><sub>(aq)</sub>",
            "NH<sub>3</sub><sub>(g)</sub>+ HCl<sub>(g)</sub>"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 12,
        "year": 1993,
        "question": "Chlorine is is used in water treatment as",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 0,
        "options": [
            "a germicide",
            "a decolorizing agent",
            "an antioxidant",
            "a coagulating agent",
            "an aerating agent"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 13,
        "year": 1993,
        "question": "Which of the following pieces of deposited if a current of 10A was passed through a solution of copper(ll) salt for 965 seconds? (1F = 96500 C)",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 2,
        "options": [
            "0.005 mole",
            "0.025 mole",
            "0.05 mole",
            "1.00 mole",
            "1.05 mole"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 14,
        "year": 1993,
        "question": "Some precious stones such as ruby and sapphire consist of aluminum oxide coloured by traces of the oxides of",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 2,
        "options": [
            "group lV elements",
            "group l metals",
            "transition metals",
            "alkaline earths",
            "the halogens"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 15,
        "year": 1993,
        "question": "Consider the reaction represented by the following equation CaCI<sub>2</sub><sub>(aq)</sub>+ H<sub>2</sub>C<sub>2</sub>O<sub>4</sub><sub>(aq)</sub>⇌ CaC<sub>2</sub>O<sub>4</sub><sub>(s)</sub>+ 2HCI<sub>(aq)</sub>. Which of the following would dissolve the precipitate of CaC<sub>2</sub>O<sub>4</sub>formed?",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 3,
        "options": [
            "Stirring the mixture vigorously",
            "Adding more calcium chloride solution",
            "lncreasing the concentration of the ethanedioic acid",
            "Adding concentrated hydrochloric acid",
            "Adding some distilled water"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 16,
        "year": 1993,
        "question": "The following gases decolorize bromine water except",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 0,
        "options": [
            "C<sub>2</sub>H<sub>6</sub>",
            "C<sub>2</sub>H<sub>4</sub>",
            "C<sub>2</sub>H<sub>2</sub>",
            "C<sub>3</sub>H<sub>4</sub>",
            "C<sub>3</sub>H<sub>6</sub>"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 17,
        "year": 1993,
        "question": "<p>What volume of distilled water should be added to 400cm3 of 2.0 mole dm-3 \\(H_{2}SO_{4}\\) to obtain 0.20 mole dm-3 of solution&gt;</p>",
        "explanation": "<p>\\(400cm^{3} \\to 2moldm^{-3}\\)</p><p>\\(0.4 dm^{3} \\to 2moldm^{-3}\\)</p><p>Multiplying in order to get the moles of the acid.</p><p>\\(0.4dm^{3} \\times 2moldm^{-3} = 0.8moles\\)</p><p>After diluting to \\(0.2moldm^{-3}\\), the new volume will be</p><p>\\(\\frac{0.8}{0.2} = 4dm^{3}\\)</p><p>Converting back to cm^3,</p><p>We have \\(4 \\times 1000cm^{3} = 4000cm^{3}\\)</p><p>Hence, the volume of water added = \\((4000 - 400)cm^{3} = 3600cm^{3}\\)</p>",
        "correctIndex": 3,
        "options": [
            "600cm-<sup>3</sup>",
            "800cm-<sup>3</sup>",
            "1,000cm-<sup>3</sup>",
            "3,600cm-<sup>3</sup>",
            "4,000cm-<sup>3</sup>"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 18,
        "year": 1993,
        "question": "Which of the following indicates the correct increasing order of oxidizing power of the halogens?",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 1,
        "options": [
            "F &lt; CI &lt; Br &lt; l",
            "l &lt; Br &lt; CI &lt; F",
            "I &lt; CI &lt; Br &lt; F",
            "Br &lt; I &lt; CI &lt; F",
            "CI &lt; F &lt; I &lt; Br"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 19,
        "year": 1993,
        "question": "Which of the following substances is a peroxide?",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 0,
        "options": [
            "Na<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>",
            "CuO",
            "Pb<sub sub>O<sub>4</sub>\n</sub>",
            "Fe<sub>2</sub>O<sub sub>\n</sub>",
            "AI<sub>2</sub>O<sub sub>\n</sub>"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 20,
        "year": 1993,
        "question": "The component of air that removed when air is bubbled into alkaline pyrogallol solution is",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 1,
        "options": [
            "carbon(lV) oxide",
            "oxgyen",
            "water vapour",
            "nitrogen",
            "helium"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 21,
        "year": 1993,
        "question": "Which of the following will not affect the degree of hardness in a sample of temporarily hard water?",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 3,
        "options": [
            "Addition of washing soda",
            "Adding of soap",
            "Treatment with carbon exchange resin",
            "Filtration",
            "Distillation"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 22,
        "year": 1993,
        "question": "Examples of polymers include the following except",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 4,
        "options": [
            "starch",
            "nylon",
            "wool",
            "perspex",
            "glass"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 23,
        "year": 1993,
        "question": "When the trioxonitrate (IV) salt of an alkali metal Y is heated, the formula of the residue is",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 1,
        "options": [
            "Y<sub>2</sub>O",
            "YNO<sub>2</sub>",
            "Y<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>",
            "Y (NO<sub>2</sub>)<sub>2</sub>",
            "YO<sub>2</sub>"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 24,
        "year": 1993,
        "question": "Which of the following compounds of tin is a strong reducing agent?",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 3,
        "options": [
            "SnCI<sub>2</sub>",
            "SnCI<sub>4</sub>",
            "SnO<sub>2</sub>",
            "SnH<sub>4</sub>",
            "Sn(OH)<sub>2</sub>"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 25,
        "year": 1993,
        "question": "In which of the following pairs are both substances deliquescent?",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 2,
        "options": [
            "CaCI<sub>2</sub>and H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>",
            "NaOH and MgSO<sub>4</sub>7H<sub>2</sub>O",
            "CaCI<sub>2</sub>and NaOH",
            "CUO and NaCI",
            "CaCO<sub>3</sub>and MgCI<sub>2</sub>"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 26,
        "year": 1993,
        "question": "Producer gas is a mixture of",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 3,
        "options": [
            "oxygen and hydrogen",
            "Hydrogen and nitrogen",
            "nitrogen and oxygen",
            "nitrogen and carbon (ll) oxide",
            "hydrogen and carbon (ll) oxide"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 27,
        "year": 1993,
        "question": "An alkene may be converted to an alkane by",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 3,
        "options": [
            "halogenation",
            "hydrolysis",
            "dehydration",
            "hydrogenation",
            "decomposition"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 28,
        "year": 1993,
        "question": "Which of the following gases are diatomic except",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 1,
        "options": [
            "nitrogen",
            "helium",
            "hydrogen",
            "fluorine",
            "oxygen"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 29,
        "year": 1993,
        "question": "Which of the following is correct about the electrons in the 1s orbital? They",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 2,
        "options": [
            "have the same spin",
            "are easier to remove than those in the 2p orbital",
            "are closest to the nucleus",
            "have the same energy as those in the 2s orbital",
            "have different magnetic quantum numbers"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 30,
        "year": 1993,
        "question": "The product of the reaction between ethanol and excess acidified K<sub>2<sub>Cr<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> is</sub></sub>",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 2,
        "options": [
            "ethanal",
            "ethylethanoate",
            "ethanoic acid",
            "ethyne",
            "ethanedioic acid"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 31,
        "year": 1993,
        "question": "When ammonium chloride is dissolved in water in a test tube, the tube feels colder showing that",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 3,
        "options": [
            "the solution is unsaturated",
            "sublimation has ocurred",
            "ammonia gas is evolved",
            "the process is endothermic",
            "condensation has occurred"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 32,
        "year": 1993,
        "question": "Zinc displaces copper from an aqueous solution of copper (ll) salt because",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 3,
        "options": [
            "copper is a transition element",
            "copper is a moderately reactive metal",
            "Zinc and copper have reducing prperties",
            "zinc is more reactive than copper",
            "zinc reacts with both acids and alkalis"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 33,
        "year": 1993,
        "question": "The alloy used for metal work and plumbing contains",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 0,
        "options": [
            "lead and tin",
            "iron and carbon",
            "copper and tin",
            "aluminium and copper",
            "lead and antimony"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    }
]